It has been nearly half a year now
since life with my Cub first began.
カブと私の生活が始まって　半年近くがたった
The school excursion was over
and I was living my usual day-to-day life.
修学旅行が終わり　私はいつもの日々を過ごしていた
My brief adventure in riding to
Kamakura after missing the bus...
乗り遅れたバスを鎌倉まで追いかけるという　ちょっとした冒険のような時間も
今となっては幻のように思える
...now seems like it was a dream.
How is your Hunter Cub riding?
ハンターカブ　調子どう？
It's only been a thousand kilometers,
so I'm still breaking it in.
まだ 1000 キロだからね　慣らし中ってとこ
But never mind me, it's getting cold.
それより… 寒い！
I feel like charging anyone
who says it's cold today a fee.
今日は寒いと言った人から罰金取りたい気分
When it's cold, it's cold.
What do you expect us to do?
寒いものは寒いんだから　しかたないじゃない
Okay, pay up. Next time,
I pull your license.
はい罰金　次は免停
I don't have any savings left
after buying my Hunter Cub.
ハンターカブ買っちゃって　貯金ももうない
Okay, I'll settle for this, instead.
じゃあ　これで勘弁してあげる
いつの間に…
When did that get there?
The seasons are changing,
and the wind is growing chillier.
季節は変わり　風は冷たさを増している
However, for some reason,
けれど　学校の空気は　なぜか不思議な熱っぽさを帯びていた
the atmosphere in the school
had taken on an unusual fervor.
Good morning.
おはよう
What's in there?
なぁに？それ
Some scraps that were in
the Home Economics room.
家庭科室にあった端切れ
使えるのがあったら使っていいって
They said if we could use any of it,
we were welcome to it.
微熱のような空気と　冷たい風
The low-grade excitement in the air
and the chill in the wind...
Autumn had arrived.
秋が来ていた
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
"2nd Year"
This might be nice.
これいいかも
Where would we use it?
どこに使う？
Hmm... Oh, Reiko-chan, good morning.
う～ん…
あっ　礼子ちゃん　おはよう
おはよう
Good morning.
Did you stop by this morning?
今朝もお店？
I sure did. You sure left early, huh?
寄ってきた
今日は早かったのね
Mm-hmm. There's so much to get ready
for the culture festival, after all.
うん
文化祭の準備があったから
"Stop by"?
お店？
Her family runs the bakery
I always buy from.
いつも私が買ってるパン屋の子
Ah...
あぁ
The culture festival, huh?
文化祭か…
Apparently, our class is putting on a bar.
うちのクラスはバールをやるらしいわ
What's a bar?
バールって？
An Italian-style café.
イタリア風のカフェ
They're serving coffee?
コーヒー出すの？
Espresso. Daiichi High
had their culture festival
エスプレッソ
一高でも文化祭があって
and they're apparently lending us
the espresso machine, the flatware,
そこで使った業務用のエスプレッソマシンやら食器やら…
and whatever else they used
for next to nothing.
まるまるタダで貸してもらえるんですって
Hmm...
What do you think about this?
これどうかなぁ
--It's nice.
--Aw...
いいね～それ
I guess work gloves aren't
going to cut it anymore.
やっぱりそろそろ軍手じゃつらいかな
If you need to change them
for something else, you should.
変えなきゃいけないなら変えればいい
It's going to get colder pretty soon.
じきにもっと寒くなる
Some streets will freeze over
and become impassable.
路面が凍って　走れない道も増えてくる
We need to do something
before that happens.
その前に　なんとかしないと
終わった～
We're done!
What are you doing today?
今日どうする～？
Um, excuse me, please!
あの～すみませ～ん
We're from the culture festival
executive committee.
文化祭実行委員で～す
So, um, we would like to decorate
the room for our culture festival bar.
えっと　文化祭のバールで　教室に飾りつけをしたいんですけど
We're going to need volunteers
to help decorate,
その飾りを作るのに人手が必要で
今日これから時間ある人　お手伝いしてもらえないでしょうか？
so anyone who has time right now,
could you please stay and help us?
Hey, what do you think?
--Why not?
--Sure.
いいよ～
I'm in, I'm in!
やるやる～
どうする？
How about it?
ありがとう　道具とかは用意してあるから
Thank you. There are materials
and things all ready to go.
んっ？
Right now, this comes first.
今はこれが先
Oh...
Is this bar going to serve coffee?
バールってコーヒーを出すの？
More like espressos and cappuccinos.
エスプレッソとかカプチーノとか
I can't wait to see it.
楽しみだね～
Where are we going?
どこへ行く？
The secondhand shops in Kofu.
甲府の中古屋を回る
I need to start thinking about getting
my Cub ready for winter, too.
私も　そろそろカブの冬支度考えないと
Ah. Let's go check out over there.
ちょっとあっち…
Huh? What gives?
あぁ　なによ！
We aren't here for that today.
今日はそっちじゃない
--Here.
--Thanks.
はい
ありがとう
There really is nothing that beats
non-slip work gloves.
やっぱり　滑り止め軍手に勝るものはないわね
Are they really that good?
そんなにいいものなの？
You know what?
知ってる？
In a number of what we refer to
as developed nations,
先進国といわれるいくつかの国では　戦闘機や輸送機のパイロットが
fighter pilots and transport pilots
still use non-slip work gloves.
いまだに滑り止め軍手を使ってるって
Which goes to show that of all the gloves
all over the world, work gloves--
それってつまり　世の中に出回ってるどんなグローブよりも軍手のほうが…
Sure, sure.
ハイハイ
Ah! Hey, listen to me! Come on, really.
あっ　ちょっと聞いてよ！
ねぇ聞いて
Sure, sure.
ハイハイ
Koguma-san!
小熊さん！
Koguma-san?
小熊さ～ん？
Okay, ready to go?
じゃ　行こうか
Huh?!
Hey, are you serious?
おい　マジかよ！
The teacher can't drive us?
先生車出せないの？
She said she had another important
errand to attend to, so no.
大事な用事があるから　だめだって
Nat-chan, didn't you ask
the teacher before?
なっちゃん　先生に頼んでくれたんじゃなかったの？
Huh? I thought you were asking her.
えっ？それアンタが話すって
Don't look at me!
俺!? 知らねえし
Forget about that, if we don't
get all that stuff over here today,
それより！今日中に荷物運んでこなきゃ
明日の準備間に合わないよ！
we won't have things ready
in time for tomorrow!
Sounds like trouble. That's too bad.
トラブル発生かぁ　大変ねぇ
Let's go.
行きましょ
Mm-hmm...
うん…
Can we get someone's parents
to drive their car?
誰か親に車出してもらうとか？
電車？
Or the train? Or, yeah, motorbikes?
そうだ　原付は？
It's an espresso machine
and other fragile stuff!
エスプレッソマシンに割れ物もあるんだよ
How dumb are you? You can't
carry that stuff on a motorbike!
バカか！原付なんかで運べるわけないだろ
Then what are we supposed to do?!
じゃあどうしろっていうんだよ！
That's what we're trying
to figure out right now!
それを今考えてるんでしょ！
Uh, everyone, stay calm.
Let's just stay calm.
みんな落ち着いて
落ち着こうよ
You still have that rig, right?
あれ… 持ってたよね
One of the dampers is shot.
ダンパーが一つ死んでる
We might be able to help you out.
なんとかできるかもしれない
U-Um, "might" how?
あ　あの… なんとかって？
Is this everything that you
need moved here today?
今日中に運ばなきゃいけないものって　これ？
"Tablecloths x 10" "Trays x 5"
"Tableware (saucers, forks)" "Coffee cups x 20"
"Showcase" "Espresso Machine"
Oh, mm-hmm.
あっ　うん
There's something I need to go borrow,
so I'm off to the faculty room.
借りておきたいものがあるから　職員室に行ってくる
They have a really good one in the gym.
あれなら　体育館に上物があったわよ
This will be a piece of cake for our Cubs.
カブなら朝飯前だよね
Nice work.
ご苦労さま
I see you managed to borrow a trailer.
リヤカー　借りられたのね
The tire pressure and axle
bearings both check out.
タイヤの空気圧も軸受けの回転も異常なし
The handle mount doesn't have
any problems with it, either.
ハンドルの取り付け部分も問題ない
I think this is going to
work over here, too.
こっちもなんとかいけそう
Who'd have guessed the day would
ever come when that would be useful?
まさかそれが役に立つ日がくるとはね
はぁ？カブの装備品の中でも最高傑作と名高いのが　この出前機よ！
Huh? This delivery rig is widely
regarded as a masterpiece,
even among all the other
Cub equipment out there.
With this thing, even an amateur driver
can keep their soba from spilling
これがあれば　たとえ運転手が素人でも
そばのつゆはこぼれないし　どんぶりも割れないんだから
and their donburi bowls from breaking!
That's why we need it. Let's get started.
だから必要
さっ　始めよう
Say, are you sure that lame
trailer has to hitch up
ねぇ　私の世界一カッコイイハンターカブと
このダサいリヤカー　どうしても繋がなきゃだめ？
to the world's coolest Hunter Cub?
My Cub is only 52 cc.
私のカブは 52cc
そっちは 110cc で　パワーもトルクも勝ってる
Yours is 110 cc, and has
more power and torque.
That is true...
だよね…
There.
よし
Not bad, huh?
悪くないわね
礼子
Reiko...
Mm-hmm.
うん
They both look all right to me.
どっちも問題なさそうね
E-Excuse me...
あ　あのぅ
Did you bring them?
持ってきてる？
They're inside.
その中
Huh? Percolators?
パーコレーター？
Be sure to learn how to
use them before you leave.
帰るまでに使い方を覚えておいて
If this trip doesn't end up successful,
運ぶのがうまくいかなかったときは
you can use those to put on
an early American saloon.
これでアーリーアメリカン・サルーンをやる
ウィンチェスター銃も　カウボーイの服も　テキサス共和国の国旗も
There's a Winchester rifle, some cowboy
clothes, a Republic of Texas flag,
サルーンに欠かせないスイングドアも　全部演劇部にある
and the swinging doors that every saloon
must have in the drama club room.
Super Ono sells canned pork and beans,
and ready-made apple pie, too.
ポークビーンズの缶詰と　出来合いのアップルパイなら
スーパーおのでも売ってるわよ
Whenever you take any action,
always have a backup plan, just in case.
何か行動を起こすときは　必ず保険として代案を用意する
Okay, we're off.
じゃあ　行ってきます
"Kofu Daiichi Prefectural High School"
Wait right here.
ここで待ってて
Okay.
は～い
Right, thanks for coming.
はい　ご苦労さま
"Faculty Room"
失礼します
Excuse me.
Ah! Long time no see!
久しぶりね！
You seem to be doing well.
元気みたいね
I'm here to borrow what we
need for our culture festival.
文化祭で必要なものを借りにきました
Oh? We were told that your teacher
was coming by to pick it up in her car.
あれ？先生が車で取りにくるって聞いてたけど
Hmm?
Ah, now I get it.
あぁ
なるほどね
It's all ready to go.
I'll bring it right out, okay?
もう準備できてるから　すぐに持ってくるわね
Okay.
はい
That's everything.
これで全部よ
I have to admit, these Cubs
of yours are amazing.
それにしても　ホントすごいわね　カブってのは
My granddad has one.
Maybe I'll ask him if I can have it.
うちのおじいちゃんも持ってるから　もらってこようかな
You should buy one new.
新車を買ったほうがいいです
The rumors that Cubs are
indestructible aren't true, after all.
カブが壊れないってのはウソだから
Riding old Cubs can be asking for trouble.
困難ですよ… 古いカブに乗るってのは
I wouldn't mind that kind of trouble.
困らせてほしいのよ
Okay, thanks.
じゃ　どうも
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございました
Be careful!
気をつけて～
"Mukawa High School Culture Festival"
"Haunted Mansion"
My name is Umahachi! In grief
for the late Omasa, Sukesada--
それがしが名は馬八　亡きおまさの無念　助定…
"Welcome to the Italian bar"
Welcome! Table for two, please!
いらっしゃいませ！
2 名様ご来店で～す！
--Welcome!
いらっしゃいませ！
Welcome. Right this way, please.
いらっしゃいませ　こちらの席どうぞ
Thank you for waiting.
お待たせしました
Espresso and lettuce-and-ham
panini, order up.
エスプレッソとレタスとハムのパニーニ　あがりました！
Coming.
う～っす！
Here, thanks.
はい　よろしくね
You bet.
はいよ～
The teacher said to figure out the cost of
our gas and submit it for reimbursement.
先生が往復のガソリン代を計算して申請しろって
ハァ… どいつもこいつも
Ugh, everyone seems to think
that gasoline is all it takes
車やバイクがガソリンだけで動くと思ってるみたいね
to keep cars and bikes running.
About a hundred yen, round trip?
往復で 100 円くらい？
I'll pretend I was going to buy a coffee,
コーヒーを買おうとして　自販機の下に落としたって思うことにするわ
but dropped my money and it rolled
under the vending machine instead.
What are you doing after this?
今日はどうする？
Hmm... I'd like to stretch my legs...
ちょっと足を伸ばして…
W-Wait! Please wait!
まっ　待って！
待ってください！
I'm sorry I haven't been able
to thank you properly.
ごめんなさい　ちゃんとしたお礼ができなくて
Here is a token of our feelings.
これ　私たちからの気持ちです
It's coffee...
コーヒーだ
Everyone is grateful to you two.
Really. But we're all so busy, so...
みんな 2 人に感謝してます　本当に
でもいろいろと忙しくて
This will do.
これで十分
Your motorbikes sure are terrific.
でも　原付ってすごいですね
I've never thought of them as terrific.
すごいと思ったことはない
It's Cubs that are terrific, Shii-chan.
すごいのはカブよ　椎ちゃん
I'd like to ride one, too.
私も乗ってみたいな
But I could never handle a motorbike.
I fall off my bicycle too much as it is.
でも　原付なんて無理　自転車でもよく転ぶのに
無理だと思ったことはやらないほうがいい
You shouldn't do anything that
you think you can't handle.
Huh?
えっ？
If you ride a Cub while you're spooked,
怖がりながらカブに乗ると
the Cub will be spooked right back
at you and fling you off of its seat.
カブもこっちを怖がって　シートから放り出したりする
乗りたい　走りたいって　思って乗らないと
They're made so that you have to want
to ride them, or they won't let you.
走ってくれないようにできている
We'll bring these back up
to the classroom later,
あとで教室まで返しにいくから
so, Shii-chan, you should hurry
on back to your counter.
椎ちゃんは早くカウンターに戻ったほうがいいわよ
Oh, then... thanks again so much, really.
あっ　じゃあ
本当にありがとうございました！
Awfully sweet, huh?
甘いな
I'll take these back. You check
out some cold-weather gloves.
返しとく
防寒グローブ　調べておいて
了解
Roger that!
Two cappuccinos!
カプチーノ 2 つ！
Okay.
は～い！
One latte macchiato, please.
ラテマキアートお願いしま～す！
I found myself unexpectedly pulled into
the middle of the culture festival.
思いがけず巻き込まれてしまった文化祭
This delicate young lady,
who was so busy taking care of matters,
テキパキと作業をこなす　その華奢な少女が
さっきよりも少し大きく見える
now looms a little larger
than she did before.
淡くて　はかない水色　それが彼女の印象だった
A pale, washed-out light blue--
that was my impression of her.
But it appears now that I was mistaken.
けど… それは間違いだったみたい
Yes, for you see...
そう… あれは…
...though the hue was a light one,
it was the color of a bright and sunny...
色見は薄くても　日差しの激しい
"Super Cub Episode 7"
"The Girl of Summer-Sky Aqua"
...summer sky.
夏空の色だ
"Super Cub Episode 7"
"The Girl of Summer-Sky Aqua"
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"Super Cub Episode 8"
"Shii's Place"
Episode 8: "Shii's Place."
第 8 話　「椎の場所」